
Project Title: Douglas-fir B class regeneration analysis

Principal Investigator: Thomson Harris 
Contact: e. thomsonharris@gmail.com, tc.harris@ubc.ca 
         p. 778-866-4198 

Part of the Mother Tree Project (MTP) at the University of British Columbia (UBC). 


Abstract:

The Douglas-fir B Class regeneration dataset (Regen_Surveys.csv) contains survival and performance metrics (height, basal diameter, and crown diameter) of interior Douglas-fir seedlings across 6 locations (Alex Fraser, Jaffray, John Prince, Narrows, Redfish, and Twobit) and metrics recording the harvest method. The dataset is recorded by individual seedling sampled. The associated climatic variables relating to the locations and seedling provenance of origin are stored in separate datasets (ClimateData_All_Provs.csv, ClimateData_AllSites.csv). After data cleaning the and merging the datasets together the dataset used in survival_fd_b.csv. Measurements in this dataset were taken in summers 2020/21.


Purpose:

This study aims at investigating the individual and interactive affects of climatic distance from provenance of origin and harvesting method on the the survival and performance of interior Douglas-fir seedlings.


Keywords:

Forestry, Silviculture, Ecology, Interior Douglas-fir, Climatic Distance, Assisted Migration, Climate Change


Taxonomic Information:

Interior Douglas-fir - Pseudotsuga menziesii var. glauca (Mayr) Franco
		      Taxonomic Serial No.: 183428


Area and Timeframe:

Locations are distributed across interior British Columbia (BC) within the span of interior Douglas-fir's range. Locations were harvested between 2017/20, planted between 2018/20, and surveyed between 2020/21. 


Data Table Attributes:

Survery Variables 
tree_number - unique identifier for each observation 
survival - binary value 1 indicates alive, 0 indicates dead. Used as a factor in analysis
location - site at which study was done
locationNo - numeric identifier of location (1 = Alex Fraser, 2 = Jaffray, 3 = John Prince, 4 = 		
	    Narrows, 5 = Redfish, 6 = Twobit)
locationF - same as "locationNo" to be used as a factor in analysis. 1st level random effect
block - unique identifier to apply blocking effect. Derived form "rep" 
blockF - same as "block: to be used as a factor in analysis, 2nd level random effect
rep - the replicate within a location 
plot - block*100 + harvestNo to create a 3rd level random effect
plotF - same as "plot" to be used as a factor in analysis
splitplotNo - location*10000 + block*100 + harvestNo to create the 4th level random effect
splitplotF - same as "splitplot" used as a factor in analysis
harvest_name - clearcut = 0% retention, seed = 10% dispersed retention (seed tree), 30Ret = 30%               	             
	       aggregate retention, 60Ret = 60% aggregate retention with thinning from below  
harvestNo - numeric identifier of harvest (1 = clearcut, 2 = seed, 3 = 30Ret, 4 = 60Ret) 
harvestF - same as "harvestNo" used as a factor in analysis 
species - species codes (Fd = interior Douglas-fir)
provenance - indicates the location the provenances was taken from, species code, and seed class
ID_tag - indicates the seedlot number_species code_seed class
provenanceNo - numeric identifier of provenance
provenanceF - same as provenanceNo to be used as a factor in analysis 
alive - same as "survival" but not used as a factor  
height - height (cm) of the seedlings 
basal_dia - basal diameter (mm) of the seedlings 
crown_dia1 - crown diameter (cm) of the seedlings measured North/South
crown_dia2 - crown diameter (cm) of the seedlings measured East/West
avg_crown_dia - the average between "crown_dia1" and "crown_dia2" (cm)
damage - binary values indicating if a seedling has any damage done to it (1 yes, 0 no)
damage_notes - note indicating what kind of damage the seedling sustained 
condition - indicates tree performance (G = good, M = moderate, P = poor, N = nearly dead, D = dead, 
	    A = alive (condition unknown))
cover - a category of crown closure
tree_cover - percentage (%) crown closure
survery_date - date that data was collected
year_planted - year the seedlings were planted  

Climatic Variables:
s_ = location (site) climate variables, p_ = provenance climate variables, d_ = difference between provenance and location climate variables 
	
MAT	- mean annual temperature (°C)
MWMT	- mean warmest month temperature (°C)
MCMT	- mean coldest month temperature ( °C)
TD	- temperature difference between MWMT and MCMT, or continentality (°C)
MAP	- mean annual precipitation (mm)
MSP 	- May to September precipitation (mm)
AHM	- annual heat-moisture index (MAT + 10)/(MAP/1000)
SHM	- summer heat-moisture index (MWMT/(MSP/1000))
DD0	- degree-days below 0°C, chilling degree-days
DD5 	- degree-days above 5°C, growing degree-days
DD_18	- degree-days below 18°C, heating degree-days
DD18	- degree-days above 18°C, cooling degree-days
NFFD	- the number of frost free days
FFP	- frost free period
PAS 	- precipitation as snow (mm) between August in previous year and July in current year 
EMT	- extreme minimum temperature over 30 years
EXT	- extreme maximum temperature over 30 years
Eref	- Hargreaves reference evaporation (mm)
CMD 	- Hargreaves climatic moisture deficit (mm)
RH	- mean annual relative humidity (%)
CMI	- Hogg's climate moisture index (mm)
DD1040 	- degree-days above 10°C and below 40°C












